<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<section title="Blender Basics" id="blender.1">

<p1>Blender has a unique interface, which is consistent across Windows, MacOS, and
Linux. It works best with a fairly large display and a three-button mouse.
A&nbsp;numeric keypad is also useful. The scroll wheel on most mice works as the third 
mouse button. If you are using an Apple mouse, you have to turn on multibutton support
in the mouse preferences settings. Blender can be configured to emulate a middle mouse button 
using the combination of left mouse button with the ALT or Option key; 
this feature can be turned on in the "Input" section
of Blender's "User Preferences", in the "File" menu.</p1>

<p>This section discusses how fundamental aspects of 3D graphics concepts work in Blender,
including geometric objects, transformations, light, material, and textures. See
<localref href="introduction.2"/> for a basic introduction to these concepts, if you have
not already read the relevant chapters of the book.</p>

<subsection title="The 3D View" id="blender.1.1">

<p>The Blender window is divided into non-overlapping sections, which are called "frames"
but are sometimes referred to as "windows" even though they are really just panes in a 
window. The frames can contain in turn contains smaller sections that I will
refer to as "panels."  The layout is very customizable.</p>

<p>If you have not customized the layout, the central frame of the window is a large
"3D View" frame that shows a view of the 3D scene that you are working on. At startup,
it contains a simple default scene. Here's what it looks like, much reduced from its
typical size, with annotations on some of its contents:</p>

<img src="blender-3d-viewport.png" width="635" height="290" tex="blender-3d-viewport.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>The 3D View frame also includes a Tools panel along the left edge and a narrow header panel
along the bottom.</np>

<p>The only thing in the 3D view that will be visible in the <word term="rendering">rendered</word>
scene is the cube. The camera represents the point of view from which the image will be made.
The point light provides illumination for the scene. The other things in the 3D View are there
to help you edit the scene or to help you to understand what you are seeing. The grid lies in
the <i>xy</i>-plane. The manipulator lets you transform the object. The 3D cursor
marks a point in 3D space that is used for several editing operations. Note the plus sign,
which reveals another panel of controls; to hide such a panel, drag its boundary to the edge of
the frame. Note the triangle in the upper right. If you drag the triangle, the frame is
split into two frames. You can remove a frame by joining it with its neighbor: Right-click
the boundary between the two frames, select "Join" from the pop-up menu, and 
click the frame that you want to discard.</p>

<break/>

<p>The 3D View window shows you a two-dimensional projection of a
three-dimensional world. You need to be able to change the view,
to look at the world from a different viewpoint. This can be done
using the mouse or using the keys on the numeric keypad or "numpad". (The numpad,
if you have one, is the group of keys to the right of the keyboard. If
you don't have a numeric keypad, you can find equivalent commands in
the "View" menu in the header panel at the bottom of the 3D View.)</p>

<p><b>Important Note:</b> In Blender, key presses are sent to the frame
that contains the mouse cursor. This does not follow standard GUI practice.
It means that the mouse cursor must be in the 3D View for
key presses to be sent to that frame. When pressing a key doesn't seem
to do anything, check the position of the mouse cursor!</p>

<p>To change the view with the mouse, use the middle mouse button. Drag with
the middle mouse button to rotate the view. Hold the shift key down while
dragging to translate the view (that is, move it up/down and left/right).
Hold the control key down while dragging to zoom the view; move the mouse up 
to zoom in, or down to zoom out. You can also zoom in and out with the scroll-wheel 
feature of the mouse.</p>

<p>The numpad, or equivalent commands in the "View" menu, can be also be used to modify and
zoom the view. But more important, they can be used to select certain common viewpoints.
The initial view in the 3D View frame is a <word>perspective projection</word> of the world
from a point that lies off all three coordinate axes. For working on the
world, however, it's generally better to use an <word>orthographic projection</word>.
Use the "5" key on the numpad to switch between projection types. Use the
numpad "1", "3", and "7" keys to select projections onto the
<i>xz</i>, <i>yz</i>, and <i>xy</i> planes. These are probably the
most useful views for modeling, and checking out the world. Using
all three projections can give you a good idea of the 3D positions
of the objects in the scene. The camera view (Numpad&nbsp;&leftquote;0") is also
very useful for modeling. Here's a list of all the numpad commands:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>Numpad 0</codedef> &mdash; View from the camera.  Hit Numpad&nbsp;0 again 
to return to the previous user view. The camera view is important because it's what
you will see when you render an image.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad 1</codedef> &mdash; View from "front," perpendicular to the xz-plane.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad 3</codedef> &mdash; View from "side," perpendicular to the yz-plane.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad 7</codedef> &mdash; View from "top," perpendicular to the xy-plane.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad 5</codedef> &mdash; Toggles between orthographic and perspective projection.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad 2,4,6,8</codedef> &mdash; Rotate the view.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad +,-</codedef> &mdash; Zoom in and out.</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad .</codedef> &mdash; Zoom to show the selected object or objects. (The "Home" key
will bring all objects into view.)</li>
<li><codedef>Numpad /</codedef> &mdash; Show <b>only</b> the selected object or objects.
Hit Numpad-/ again to return to the full view. This feature is very useful when editing
an object.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Adding and Transforming Objects" id="blender.1.2">

<p>Changing the view does not modify the contents of the world.
To do that, you need editing operations such as adding objects to the world. This
is where the 3D&nbsp;cursor comes in. The 3D&nbsp;cursor
is labeled in the above image of the 3D View frame. A&nbsp;newly added object is
always added to the world at the position of the 3D cursor.</p>

<p>You must position the 3D cursor <b>before</b> adding the object.
The 3D cursor is positioned by clicking on the 3D&nbsp;View window with the left mouse button.
The 3D cursor exists in three-dimensional
space. You can't tell where it is by looking at the world from just one
point of view. Typically, you would check the position of the 3D
cursor from several viewpoints by rotating the view or by using the Keypad 1, 3, and 7 keys
to switch between views.</p>

<p>Another way to position the 3D cursor is with the "Snap" menu,
which you can call up by pressing SHIFT-S while the mouse cursor is in the 3D&nbsp;Vew window.
(Remember that the cursor must be in the 3D View frame for keystrokes to be
sent to that frame.)  You can also find the Snap menu as a submenu in the "Object" menu below the 3D View.
This menu contains commands for positioning the cursor as well as for positioning objects.
For example, use "Cursor To Center" to move the 3D cursor to the point (0,0,0).</p>

<p>Once you have the 3D cursor in position, use the "Add" menu
to add an object to the world. You can pop up the Add menu at the mouse
position by hitting Shift-A, or you can find it in the header panel below the 3D View.
The Add menu has submenus for adding several types of objects. I suggest that
you stick with mesh objects at first. (A&nbsp;<word term="polygonal mesh"/>
mesh is a surface made up of polygons or a curve made up of line segments.)  Various
mesh objects are available in the "Mesh" submenu of the Add menu. For example,
A UVSphere is a sphere divided into segments by lines of latitude and longitude.
An ICOSphere is divided into triangles. A Plane is actually just
a rectangle. (When you first start Blender, the object in the
default scene is a mesh Cube.) </p>

<p>When adding certain types of objects, there are some options you can change.
When you add the object, a panel containing these options
appears in the lower left region of the 3D View frame.
The following image shows part of that panel for a Mesh UVSphere.
You can change the number of Segments and Rings,
which are the number of subdivisions around the equator of the sphere and the number from the
north pole to the south pole.</p>

<img src="blender-add-uvsphere.png" width="161" height="179" tex="blender-add-uvsphere.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>The numerical input widgets in this panel are examples of Blender's funny input
buttons. Here's how to use such buttons:  You can click the
button, type in a value, and press return. You can click the arrows
at the ends of the button to increase/decrease the value. Or you
can drag the mouse left-to-right or right-to-left on the button to change
the value.</np>

<break/>

<p>Objects can be "selected."  When you apply an edit operation
to the 3D&nbsp;View window, it affects the selected object or objects. When
you add an object to the scene, the new object is automatically selected.
You can select an object by <b>right-clicking</b> it. Selected objects
are shown outlined in orange. You can select multiple objects by holding down
the Shift key as you right-click the objects. When multiple objects
are selected, certain operations only apply to the most recently
selected object. That object is shown in a slightly brighter orange.
A manipulator, shown in the
image at the beginning of this section, appears at the selected object or
at the center of the group of selected objects. 
You can move the selected object or objects in the direction of the coordinate axes by dragging
the arrow heads on the manipulator axes. You can change the manipulator to one that
can be used for <word>rotation</word> or <word>scaling</word> instead of 
<word>translation</word>. Look for the manipulator controls below the 3D View:</p>

<img src="blender-manipulator-controls.png" width="161" height="36" tex="blender-manipulator-controls.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>Clicking the icon on the left end of this group of controls will toggle the visibility of
the manipulator. The next three icons select the type of manipulator.</np>

<p>To <b>delete</b> the selected object or objects, just hit the X key or the Delete key. 
You will be asked to confirm the deletion. (Remember that the mouse cursor 
must be in the 3D window for it to get keyboard commands. (This is the last time
I will say this.))</p>

<p>As you modify the world, you can undo most operations by pressing
Control-Z. That includes adding, deleting, and editing objects.
Conrol-Shift-Z is the Redo operation.</p>

<break/>

<p>There are other, more general ways to transform objects using the keyboard and mouse
instead of the manipulator.  Note that
you do <b>not</b> simply click-and-drag an object to move it!
Instead, select the object or objects you want to transform by right-clicking
them, then apply the transformation as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Press the "G" key. (G&nbsp;stands for "grab".)  Move the mouse
       <b>without holding down any button</b>. You can move the object
       in the plane of the screen only. Click with the
       left mouse button to finish. Click with the right mouse button
       to abort. (Hitting return will also finish; hitting Escape will also abort.) 
       After hitting the "G" key, you can hit
       "X", "Y", or "Z" to constrain motion to one axis.
       (Alternatively, you can <b>start</b> moving an
       object if you just right-click and start dragging. However,
       releasing the right-mouse does <b>not</b> end the move!  You still
       have to end it as described here.)</li>
 <li>Press the "S" key. Without holding down any mouse key, move the mouse towards or away from the object 
       to change its size.  The size changes in all three dimensions. 
       Click with the left mouse button to finish. Click with the right mouse button
       to abort. After hitting "S", you can hit "X", "Y", or "Z" to scale the
       object in the direction of one axis only.</li>
 <li>Press the "R" key. Without holding down any mouse key, move the mouse to rotate the object
       around a line perpendicular to the screen. Click with the left 
       mouse button to finish. Click with the right mouse button
       to abort. <b>If you hit "R" a second time, you can
       freely rotate the object.</b>  After hitting "R", you can hit "X", "Y", or "Z" to rotate the
       object about the specified axis.</li>  
</ul>   
 
<p>Whether rotating, scaling, or translating, you can hold the
Control key down to limit the changes, such as to integral amounts
while translating or to multiples of ten degrees while rotating.
Also, you can use the arrow keys to make small adjustments.</p>

<p>You can get yourself real confused if you don't remember to
press the left or right mouse button to complete a transformation 
operation. You can't do anything else until the operation is completed.</p>

<p>All these operations can be applied to the camera, just as they
are applied to any other object. You can move and point the
camera to get the view of the world that you want to see when you
render an image. You can even apply transformations
to the camera while in the camera view (Numpad&nbsp;0), as long
as the camera is the selected object. This can
be a good way to get the exact view that you want for an image.</p>

<p>Note that rotations and scaling are relative to the "center" of
the selected object or group of objects, the point where the manipulator 
is drawn. This center point is not necessarily at the geometric center 
of the object.</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Edit Mode" id="blender.1.3">
<p>Ordinary transformations (and many other operations) are applied to an
object as a whole. Sometimes, however, you want to work on the vertices, edges, or
faces of an object. For that, you use "edit&nbsp;mode."</p>

<p>To enter Edit Mode for the selected object, press TAB. When
in Edit Mode, press TAB to exit Edit Mode. In Edit Mode, you can
select individual vertices and groups of vertices. You can select
a face by selecting all the vertices of that face. You can select
an edge by selecting both vertices of that edge. You can scale,
rotate, and translate selected elements in the usual way,
with the S, R, and G keys, or using the manipulator. You 
can delete things with the X key. Hitting the W key will pop
up a large menu of actions that you can take on the selected
elements.</p>

<p>In Edit Mode, selected vertices and faces are orange. 
The picture on the left below shows a cube in edit
mode with all vertices selected. In the second picture,
only the vertices of the top face are selected. In can be easier
to work in Edit Mode using a "<word>wireframe</word>" view instead of the
default "solid" view. Hit the "Z" key to toggle between the
two views. The third picture shows the cube as a wireframe,
with the manipulator hidden to make it even easier to see what
you are doing.</p>

<img src="blender-edit-mode.png" width="550" height="206" tex="blender-edit-mode.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<p>When you first enter Edit Mode for a mesh object, all of its vertices
are selected. Pressing the "A" key will deselect all vertices.
If you press the "A" key when no vertices are selected, all the
vertices will be selected. You can select a vertex by right-clicking near it.
Hold down the shift key while right-clicking to select multiple 
vertices. Shift-right-click a selected vertex to de-select it.
There is a way to add a several vertices to the
selection at the same time:  Hit the "B" key. You can then draw a "box" by left-clicking
and dragging with the mouse. Vertices within the box when you release the mouse button are added to
the set of selected vertices. This is an easy way, for example,
to select all the vertices at the top of a cube. (It can be easier to select
sets of vertices in wireframe mode.)  You might have
to change the point of view several times while selecting the
vertices and performing operations on them.</p>

<p>There are a lot of things you <b>can't do</b> in Edit Mode,
so don't forget that you have to press the TAB key to get out
of that mode!</p>

<p>By the way, the "Z" key can be used outside of Edit Mode to toggle between a solid
and a wireframe view of the selected object. And the "A" and "B" keys can  be used outside of
Edit Mode for selecting sets of objects. If you get lost in the 3D view, use the A
key to select all objects, then hit Numpad-period; this will bring all objects into view.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Light, Material, and Texture" id="blender.1.4">

<p>Lights in a scene don't affect the appearance of objects in the 3D View.
<word term="lighting">Lighting</word> is used only when an image of the scene is rendered. If there
are no lights in the scene, then no objects will be visible in the
rendered image.</p>

<p>There is already one light in the default scene, which
you can drag around so that it best illuminates your objects.
An easy way to be sure of lighting all visible objects is to
place the light at the position of the camera.
You can add additional lights, using the "Lamp" submenu in
the "Add" menu. "Lamp" is Blender's term for "light."  As for
any object, a new lamp appears at
the position of the 3D cursor. You might have to
add several lamps to light your scene well.</p>

<p>There are several kinds of lamp in the "Lamp" submenu. A "Point" lamp gives off
light in all directions. The light in the initial
scene is a point lamp. A "Sun" means light shining
in parallel rays from some direction, indicated by a line drawn
from the lamp in the 3D view. A "Spot" is a spotlight that gives off a cone of light. You need to
aim a sun or spotlight at the objects you want to illuminate. Change the direction
of a sun or spot by rotating it.</p>

<break/>

<p>The default color of an object is gray. To change this,
you have to add a "<word>material</word>" to the object and set the
properties of that material. (The cube in the
start-up world has a material; new objects that you add don't.)
To work on materials, use the Properties Editor frame, which you
can find to the right of the 3D view.  That frame allows you to
set all kinds of properties of objects. At the top of the frame there is a 
a row of buttons that select which group of properties you
want to work on. The buttons that appear in this row depend
on what kind of object is currently selected, although some
are always present. Here are the
buttons that are shown when the selected object is a mesh. You might
have to expand the width of the frame to see them all in the Blender
window:</p>

<img src="blender-property-header.png" width="579" height="226" tex="blender-property-header.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>In this picture, the Materials button has been clicked.
With the materials button selected, 
the rest of the editor panel, below the header, is filled with controls
for setting the material properties of the selected object.
Most of the controls don't appear until a material has been added
to the object. If there is no material, you will see a "New" button
in the properties frame. (The Properties Editor view can look empty because its
contents have been scrolled out of sight. If you don't see anything, check the
scrollbar!)  Click the "New" button to add a new material to the object,
or click the icon to the left of "New" to use a material that already exists.
The full set of controls will appear. Here's what you will see
in the top part of the frame:</np>

<img src="blender-material-properties.png" width="576" height="490" tex="blender-material-properties.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<break/>

<p>A <word>texture</word> makes the color or some other property of an object vary from point to point.
One type of texture copies colors from an image, effectively painting the
image on the surface of the object. This is called an <word>image texture</word>.
Alternatively, the color can be computed algorithmically from the
coordinates of the point. This is called a <word>procedural texture</word>.</p>

<p>A texture should only be added to an object that already has
a material, since texture is considered to be part of the material.
To add a texture to an object, select the object (and add a material if it doesn't already have one!).
Click on the texture button in the header of the Properties Editor frame. If the object already
has a texture, you will be able to edit it. Otherwise, click the
"New" button, or select an existing texture from the list, just as for the material. Once you've
added the texture, a "Type" popup menu will appear where
you can choose the type of texture that you want to use.</p>

<p>One type of texture is an Image texture. If you choose that
type, you will see an "Open" button that you can click to select
the image file that you want to use as a texture. </p>

<p>Most of the remaining texture types are procedural textures.
You might try "Marble", "Clouds", and "Wood".
When you select one of these, controls appear that
allow you to modify the
appearance of the texture. The Marble pattern, for example,
usually looks better if it's set to "Sharp" or "Sharper"
rather than "Soft."  In general,
you should set the "Coordinates" in the
"Mapping" section of the Material controls to "Generated" to get 
the best effect.</p>

<p>The Clouds, Wood, and Marble textures make patterns of
two colors. One color is the diffuse material color of the object.
The other is set as a property of the texture (look for the
color patch in the "Influence" section of the texture properties panel). By default, the second
color is an ugly magenta, which you will want to change.</p>

<p>To see what the texture will look like on an object, go back to the material
properties by clicking the Material button in the header.</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Saving Your Work" id="blender.1.5">

<p>The 3D window shows positions, sizes, and colors of your objects. To see a fully
rendered scene from the point of view of the camera, hit the F12 key.
To dismiss that view, hit Escape or F11. There are are also commands in
the "Render" menu, at the top of the Blender menu, that do the same things. Many aspects of the scene, including
textures, transparency, and shadows, do not appear in the 3D&nbsp;View window. To
see them, you have to render an image.</p>

<p>When you render an image, the image is created but it is not saved anywhere. To save
it, use the F3 key while the rendered image is on screen, or use the "Save as Image"
command from the "Image" menu at the bottom of the frame where the rendered image is displayed.
The size and default format of the image are set in the Properties Editor frame, with the
"Render" button selected.</p>

<p>When you save an image&mdash;or need to choose a file from the file system for
some other reason&mdash;you will see the Blender File Browser frame. The File
Browser, like the rest of Blender, uses a non-standard interface. However, it is
not difficult to use. You can browse the file system using the directory listing in
the center of the frame. Click the top item in the list (shown as "<code>..</code>")
to go up one directory. Shortcuts to some directories are listed along the left edge
of the frame. Two input fields at the top of the frame show the selected directory
and file name. For saving a file, you should edit the file name by hand. Click the
"Save" or "Cancel" button to the right of the input fields to finish.</p>

<break/>

<p>To save your entire Blender session, use the "Save" command in the "File" menu.
A Blender session is stored in a file with the extension ".blend". Opening a .blend
file will restore the saved state of the program. If you use the "Save Startup File"
command in the "File" menu, Blender will save the current state of the program in
a .blend file somewhere in your home directory. After that, when you start Blender,
it will open that file as the starting point for
your session, instead of the usual initial scene.
This feature allows you customize your startup environment.</p>


</subsection>


<subsection title="More Features" id="blender.1.6">

<p>We have covered a lot of basic ground about
Blender, but before looking at more advanced modeling and animation, 
there is a little more background
information that will be useful&dots;</p>


<p><b>Duplicating; Data versus Object</b>:
An object on the screen has two aspects:  The basic data for the object and the transform 
that has been applied to that data. The data for a mesh, for example, would be the
coordinates of all its vertices in the mesh's own coordinate system. It also includes
the material properties of the mesh. It's possible for objects to share the same data
but have different transforms. Suppose you want to duplicate an object. 
There are two ways to do it. You can select the object and hit SHIFT-D. This will make
a copy of the selected object.  The copy will be in the exact same place as the
original, but will be in "grab" mode so that you can immediately move it away from
the original by moving the mouse. When you duplicate an object in this way, with SHIFT-D,
you make copies of both the object and its data. That is, you really do get a complete copy.
However, you can also duplicate the selected object by hitting ALT-D. When you use ALT-D,
the two objects <i>share the same data</i>; only their transforms are different. This means
that if you go into Edit Mode and change one of the object's vertices, the same changes
are applied to the other object. If you change the material on one of the objects, the
other one changes as well. On the other hand, if you transform one of the objects by
moving, scaling, or rotating it, the change does not affect the copy. This type of
copy can actually be very useful&mdash;and it can save memory since there is only one copy
of the object data.</p>


<p><b>Parenting</b>:
One object can be a "parent" of another. This allows you
to create <word term="hierarchical modeling">hierarchical models</word>. 
When you drag, rotate, or scale a parent, all its child objects
are transformed as a group along with the parent. But child objects can still have
their own transformations within the group. Furthermore, a child of one object can be
a parent of another object, so you can do multi-level hierarchical graphics. If you want to group 
several objects, and there is no obvious parent, you should consider parenting all the
objects to an empty&nbsp;object, made with the "Empty" command
in the "Add" menu. To create a parent
relationship, select the child object or objects, then shift-right-click the parent to add it to
the selection. Hit CONTROL-P. You will have to confirm that you want to make a parent.
A dotted line will join the child to its parent in the 3D View.
To delete a parent relationship, select the child, hit ALT-P, and select "Clear Parent"
from the popup menu.</p>

<p><b>Smooth Shading</b>:  By default, mesh objects have a "faceted" appearance where
the polygons that make up the mesh look flat. The effect is called <word>flat shading</word>.
Sometimes this is correct, but often
you want to use the mesh as an approximation for a smooth object, such as a sphere.
In that case you want to use <word>smooth shading</word> instead.
To select between flat shading and smooth shading for a mesh object, select the
object and look in the "Tools" panel to the left of the 3D&nbsp;View.
You'll find two "Shading" buttons, marked "Flat" and "Smooth," for selecting the type of
shading. Setting a mesh object to use smooth shading does not change the geometry of the
object; it just uses different normal vectors (see <localref href="gl1light.1.3"/>).</p>

<p><b>Layers</b>:
Blender has "layers", where each layer can contain
its own collection of objects. When several layers are shown in the 3D View, their objects
are not actually layered on top of each other; all the objects from all the visible layers
are shown intermingled in one 3D scene. The point is that 
you can show and hide objects by turning the layers that contain them on and off.
The main point is to allow you to work on objects in one layer
without being confused by the objects in the other layers. Blender has exactly 20
layers, and they are controlled by a set of 20 small buttons in the
header panel at the bottom of the 3D View. The buttons look like this:</p>

<img src="blender-layer-buttons.png" width="117" height="38" tex="blender-layer-buttons.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<np>A dot in a layer button means that that layer contains one or more objects. Layers
that are selected for viewing are shown in a darker gray.
You can click a layer button to select just that layer. You can shift-click
to select multiple layers. You can move objects from one layer to another:  Select
the object and hit the "M" key; a&nbsp;set of layer buttons will pop up where you can 
select the layer to which you want to move the object. You can use hidden layers to store
objects that you have worked on, but that you don't want to be visible at the moment.</np>


<p><b>Naming</b>:
In Blender, objects, textures, materials, scenes, etc., all have <i>names</i>.
Blender automatically assigns generic names such as "Cube.002" when you create or
duplicate an object. Sometimes, you need to know something's
name. An example is the "text on curve" feature that will be discussed
in the <localref href="blender.2">next section</localref>. 
To make it easier to identify an object, you might want to use a more meaningful name.
Names are generally displayed in editable boxes. You can just click the box and
enter a new name. For objects, the name is displayed in the "Object" controls
in the Properties Editor frame. </p>



<p><b>Scenes and Screens</b>:
A "scene" in Blender is its own 3D world. Each scene can contain unique objects,
but it is also possible for scenes to share objects. There is a popup menu at the top
of the Blender window that you can use to create new scenes and to switch from one
scene to another. To its left is a popup menu for selecting a "screen."  A screen
is a customized layout for the Blender window. The two menus look like this:</p>

<img src="blender-scene-and-screen.png" width="401" height="36" tex="blender-scene-and-screen.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<np>Click the icon at the left end of the control to pop up the menu.
Click the center of the control to enter a new name for the current item.
Click the "X" on the right end to delete the item. Click the "+"
sign to create a new screen or scene. When you create a new screen, it is a
duplicate of the current screen. When you create a new scene, you will get 
several options in a popup menu:  "New" will create an
empty scene. "Link Objects" will create  a scene that contains the same objects as
the current scene, with the same transforms; if you move an object in one scene,
it also moves in the other one. You can then add new
objects later that will be in only one of the scenes. You might use this, for example, if you
want to set up a common static background world and then make several scenes that show
different "actors" doing different things in different scenes, but with the
same environment. With "Link Object Data", objects
in the two scenes share the same data but not the same transform; this lets you have
the same actors doing different things in different scenes, with the same
environment. "Full Copy" copies both the
transforms and data, so the scenes look the same originally, but really have no shared data
in common.</np>



</subsection>

</section>
