<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<intro>

<p1>In this chapter, we turn to <newword>WebGL</newword>, the version of <word>OpenGL</word>
for the Web. <i>Three.js</i>, which was covered in the <localref href="threejs">previous chapter</localref>,
uses WebGL for 3D graphics. Of course, it is more difficult to use WebGL directly, but doing
so gives you full control over the graphics hardware. And learning it will be a good introduction
to modern graphics programming.</p1>

<p>There have been many versions of OpenGL. WebGL 1.0 is based on OpenGL ES 2.0, a version
designed for use on embedded systems such as smart phones and tablets. OpenGL ES 1.0
was very similar to OpenGL 1.1, which we studied in <localref href="gl1geom"/>
and <localref href="gl1light"/>. However, the 2.0 version of OpenGL&nbsp;ES introduced
major changes. It is actually a smaller, simpler <word>API</word> that puts more responsibility
on the programmer. For example, functions for working with transformations, such
as <i>glRotatef</i> and <i>glPushMatrix</i>, were eliminated from the API, making the
programmer responsible for keeping track of transformations. WebGL does not
use <i>glBegin/glEnd</i> to generate geometry, and it doesn't use function such
as <i>glColor*</i> or <i>glNormal*</i> to specify attributes of vertices. Nevertheless,
it will turn out that much of what you learned in previous chapters will carry over to
WebGL.</p>

<p>There are two sides to any WebGL program. Part of the program is written in
<word>JavaScript</word>, the programming language for the web. The second part is
written in <word>GLSL</word>, a language for writing "shader" programs that run on the
<word>GPU</word>. We will try to always be clear about which language we are
talking about.</p>

<p>For this introductory chapter about WebGL, we will stick to basic 
2D graphics. You will learn about the structure of WebGL programs. You will learn
most of the JavaScript side of the API, and you learn how to write and use simple
shaders. In the <localref href="webgl3d">next chapter</localref>, we will move
on to 3D graphics, and you will learn a great deal more about GLSL.</p>

</intro>
